Guide to the Edward Charles "Teddy Blue" Abbott papers 1865-1963
Montana Historical Society
Edward Charles "Teddy Blue" Abbott papers
1865-1963
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 51
Abbott, E. C. (Edward Charles), 1860-1939
1.9 linear feet
Edward Charles "Teddy Blue" Abbott was a Giltedge, Montana, cattleman, Fergus County school trustee, and author. This collection contains records from Teddy Blue Abbott and his family, including general correspondence, financial records, clippings, legal documents, and writings. The latter contains handwritten and typed drafts of Abbott's autobiography, We Pointed Them North (1939).
Collection is open for research.
Edward Charles "Teddy Blue" Abbott was born December 17, 1860, in Cranwich Hall, Norfolk County, England. In 1871, he moved to the United States with his father, J.B. Abbott. They traveled to Texas, eventually purchased a cattle herd, and drove it north to Nebraska. Teddy Blue settled with his family at the end of the Texas cattle trail near Lincoln, Nebraska. In 1883, he entered Montana Territory with a herd of longhorns, and two years later, signed on with the DHS Ranch at Fort Maginnis. He became engaged to Mary Stuart, daughter of one of his employers, Granville Stuart. The couple married on September 29, 1889, and settled on the 3 Deuce Ranch at Giltedge, Montana. They had ten children: Katie Anne (1890-1986); Charles Edward (1892-1959); Mary E. (1895-1904); William (1897-1897); Elsie Blue (1898-1995); Granville Stuart (1901-1990); James Jefferson (1903-1988); William Robert [Robert] (1906-1964); Teddie Blue [Ted] (1909-1982); and Mary Inez (1915-1984).
Teddy Blue Abbott was a longtime member of the Montana Stockgrowers Association, he served six years on the Montana Stock Commission for Fergus County, thirty years as a member of the Democratic Central Committee, and sixteen years as a school trustee. In 1924, he was an unsuccessful candidate for the Montana State Legislature. In 1938, Abbott collaborated with Helena Huntington Smith on his autobiography, We Pointed Them North, the story of his years as a cowpuncher on the Texas cattle drives and his experiences on Montana's open range in the 1880s. Teddy Blue Abbott died of pneumonia on April 7, 1939, days after the book was published.
Mary Stuart Abbott was born February 2, 1870, in Deer Lodge, Montana, to Granville and Arbonnie Stuart. She died February 5, 1967, in Lewistown, Montana.
The collection consists of five subgroups: Teddy Blue Abbott, Mary Stuart Abbott, Mary Inez Abbott Swanson Matejcek, Robert and Granville Abbott, and Katie Stuart. The Teddy Blue Abbott Subgroup contains ten series: Incoming Correspondence (1889-1946, undated), Outgoing Correspondence (1888-1939), Miscellaneous Correspondence (1909-1939, undated), Court Papers (1910), Diaries (1887-1890), Financial Records (1907-1963), Legal Documents (1888-1941), Writings (1938, undated), Miscellany (1888-1939, undated), and Clippings (1920-1939, undated). The Incoming Correspondence includes letters from Abbott family members, the Democratic Central Committee for Fergus County, Kenneth M. Ireland, Oscar O. Mueller, D.J. O'Malley and Mary Alicia O'Malley, Margot Pringle, Charles M. Russell, Helena Huntington Smith (Pringle), Mary Stuart before she married Teddy Blue, and Johnnie W. Young. The Outgoing Correspondence includes letters to Helena Huntington Smith (Pringle) and Mary Stuart before she married Teddy Blue. The Miscellaneous Correspondence includes letters between the U.S. General Land Office and the U.S. Land Office in Lewistown, from publisher Farrar and Rinehart to Helena Huntington Smith (Pringle), and from James Fergus to the Lewistown "Argus" concerning the funeral of Mrs. Granville Stuart. The Court Papers consist of the testimony of Stephen E. Suitor in his trial for the murder of Tom Burke and miscellaneous other cases. The Legal Documents include mortgages, warranty deeds, leases, recorded brands, and a homestead certificate. Some plats and land descriptions can be found in the Miscellany series. The Diaries series contains four diaries: 1887-1888, 1888-1889 (includes entries at the end from 1910, 1912, 1938, and a list of his children and when they were born), 1889 (includes a list of wedding expenses), and 1890 (includes an extensive list of expenses, some from 1889). The Miscellany series contains 18 notebooks, which also include diary entries and financial notations. The Financial Records contain check stub books (1907-1923), insurance policies, promissory notes, tax statements, a list of brands, and miscellaneous bills of sale, receipts, and invoices. The Writings series consists of handwritten and typed drafts of We Pointed Them North. A promotional pamphlet for We Pointed Them North can be found in the Miscellany series. Also in the Miscellany series is a campaign statement by E.C. Abbott as a candidate for the state legislature, a legislative bill for the disposition of strays, and precinct lists of registered voters. The Clippings series contains miscellaneous newspaper articles by Abbott; obituaries of Abbott, and of brother-in-law Edward Stuart and son Charles E. Abbott, Jr.; and historical articles.
The Mary Stuart Abbott Subgroup consists of a General Correspondence series (1888-1951, undated), Financial Records series (1899-1948), Legal Documents series (1909-1938), and a Miscellany series (1885-1934). Correspondents include Helena Huntington Smith (Pringle), Abbott and Stuart family members, and D.J. O'Malley. Financial records include tax statements, bank statements, and Land Office receipts. The miscellaneous legal documents include seed liens, crop mortgages, and land patents. The miscellany series contains an autograph book (1885) and invitations (1918-1934).
The Mary Inez Abbott Swanson Matejcek Subgroup consists of a General Correspondence series (1931-1953), Court Papers series, Financial Records series, and a Miscellany series. The correspondents include Helena Huntington Smith (Pringle) and Jack Abbott. The court papers consist of a subpoena (1949) and the financial records contain a tax assessment list (1952). The miscellany series contains a sketching instruction book (1857) and a sketchbook (undated) used by Mary and by James and Granville Stuart.
The Robert and Granville Abbott Subgroup contains two series, Incoming Correspondence, consisting of a postcard (undated) from a friend to Granville Abbott, and Miscellany, consisting of notebooks (1915-1919) of Robert and Granville.
The Katie Stuart Subgroup contains Katie Stuart's autograph book (1881-1887). Katie Stuart was Mary Stuart Abbott's older sister. She died of tuberculosis and the Abbotts postponed their wedding for six months out of respect for her.
Arranged by subgroups with topical series.
Acquisition information available upon request.
Photographs and printed material were transferred from this collection to the MHS Photo Archives and MHS Library respectively.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Abbott, E. C. (Edward Charles), 1860-1939
Fort Maginnis (Mont.); Gilt Edge (Mont.)
Authors; Cattle raising--Montana; Cattle drives
Montana; Pioneers; Agriculture
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Teddy Blue Abbott
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Abbott Family (correspondents include J.B. Abbott, Annie Abbott, Frank Abbott, Jack Abbott, Orland Abbott), 1889-1900, 1910, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - A (correspondents include Alliance Oil Company, A.E. Allison), 1890-1938 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - B (correspondents include Barbara Bayne, Keith Blake and Company, J.J. Brennan, Mrs. E.E. Brown, Bud and Daisy Burdett, Winnie Burnett), 1889-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - C (correspondents include Charles S. Caldwell, Marjorie Carter, Central Montana Production Credit Corporation, E.K. Cheadle, Jo M. Colgan), 1898-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Democratic Central Committee for Fergus County, 1916 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - F (correspondents include Farrar and Rinehart, Fergus County, First National Bank of Lewistown), 1900-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - G (correspondents include Gertrude Garrett, Carol O'Donnell Getz, Lou C. Gillett), 1937, undated (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - H (correspondents include A.W. Hammer, Hattie Hawkins, Robert L. Hedges), 1907-1941 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - Kenneth M. Ireland, 1935 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
    - J (correspondents include Mrs. W.H. Johnson, Hazel Gifford Julson), 1939-1942 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Kemp family (postcard), undated (Box-folder 1 / 11)
    - L (correspondents include Robert E. Latimer, T.J. Lauderdale, C.S. Lenair), 1937-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - M (correspondents include J. and W.C. Mackenzie, William Mackey, Thomas B. Marquis, Meri An Mather, E.K. Matson, Valerie McLean Millard, George R. Milburn, Montana Board of Stock Commissioners, Montana State Veterinarian M.E. Knowles, Mountain Meadow Stock Farm, Oscar O. Mueller), 1896-1946 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
    - N (correspondents include Mike Nettik, A.C. Nippert), 1928-1934 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
    - O (correspondents include Budd O'Donnell, D.J. O'Malley, Mary Alicia O'Malley, Bert Orr), 1929-1939, undated (Box-folder 1 / 15)
    - P (correspondents include Parmley Billings Library, J.E. Pinkley, Margot Pringle, "The Producer"), 1901-1938 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
    - R (correspondents include F.M. Richmond, John E. Ritch, Minnie R. Ritch, C.O. Robinson, Charles M. Russell, J.H. Rutter, L.H. Rutter), 1917-1939, undated (Box-folder 1 / 17)
    - Helena Huntington Smith [Mrs. Henry F. Pringle], 1937-1939, undated (Box-folder 1 / 18)
    - Mary Stuart [later Abbott], 1888-1889, undated (Box-folder 1 / 19)
    - S (correspondents include George A. Shirley, Marcus Snyer, Pink Simms, Mrs. Roy Stover, Eddie Stuart), 1888-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
    - T (correspondents include Edmond G. Toomey, James M. Tucker), 1896, 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
    - U (correspondents include U.S. Farm Credit Administration, U.S. General Land Office, U.S. Office of Indian Affairs), 1938-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
    - V (correspondents include Vigilance Club of Virginia City, Leonard Van Ess), 1938-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
    - W (correspondents include Glendolin Damon Wagner, Robert Walsh, Harold Warnes, Western Sales Agency, Ruth Wiggs, Belle Winston, Wright Land and Investment Company), 1912-1938 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
    - Johnnie W. Young, 1939 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
    - Unidentified, 1910-1938, undated (Box-folder 1 / 26)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - To Helena Huntington Smith [Mrs. Henry F. Pringle], 1938-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 27)
    - To Mary Stuart [later Abbott], 1888-1889 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Letters between U.S. General Land Office and U.S. Land Office in Lewistown, publisher Farrar and Rinehart to Helena Huntington Smith [Mrs. Henry Pringle], James Fergus to Lewistown Argus re funeral of Mrs. Granville Stuart), 1909-1939, undated (Box-folder 1 / 29)
  - Court Papers
    - Testimony of Stephen E. Suitor in his trial for the murder of Tom Burke; miscellaneous summons, etc., in other cases, 1910 (Box-folder 1 / 30)
  - Diaries
    - Diaries, 1887-1888; 1888-1889 (Box-folder 1 / 31)
    - Diaries, 1889; 1890 (Box-folder 1 / 32)
  - Financial Records
    - Check stub books (25 books), 1907-1923 (Box-folder 2 / 1-6)
    - Insurance policies (includes life insurance, fire insurance on ranch property), 1896, 1904-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - Promissory notes, 1890-1938 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
    - Tax statements, 1889-1940 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
    - Miscellaneous (includes bank deposit slips, list of brands, horse pasture rentals, bills of sale, receipts, invoices, etc.), 1889-1963 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - Legal Documents
    - Mortgages and warranty deeds, 1889-1936 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
    - Leases and recorded brands, 1888-1941 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
    - Miscellaneous (includes homestead certificate, road notice, agreement for sale of mining interest, seed lien, motor vehicle licenses), 1888-1936 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Writings
    - We Pointed Them North (typed draft of introduction by Helena Huntington Smith), 1938 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
    - We Pointed Them North (typed draft of chapters 1-2), 1938 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
    - Miscellaneous handwritten articles (includes "Christmas at Fort Maginnis," "Story of a Reformed Cowboy," "One Day on a Roundup," "The Texas Trail," "Forty Years a Cow Puncher" [song], "'81 Trail," "Trail in '83," and untitled fragments), undated (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Miscellany
    - Campaign statement by E.C. Abbott as candidate for the state legislature, circa 1924 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
    - Legislative bill for disposition of strays, undated (Box-folder 3 / 9)
    - Notebooks (14: includes diary entries, financial notations, etc.; dates vary widely), 1888-1938 (Box-folder 3 / 10-14)
    - Notebooks (4: includes diary entries, financial notations, etc.), 1921-1926 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
    - Plats, land descriptions, undated (Box-folder 4 / 2)
    - Precinct lists of registered voters in Gilt Edge, and campaign cards, 1914, 1916, undated (Box-folder 4 / 3)
    - Promotional pamphlet for "We Pointed Them North", 1939 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
    - Miscellaneous (includes "Balenton Bray" by Ella Anderson, "In Loving Remembrance of Mrs. Arbonnie Stuart," cards, notes, programs, etc.), undated (Box-folder 4 / 5)
  - Clippings
    - Miscellaneous (includes articles by Abbott, obituaries, historical articles), 1920-1939, undated (Box-folder 4 / 6)
- Mary Stuart Abbott
  - General Correspondence
    - Helena Huntington Smith [Mrs. H.F. Pringle], 1938-1940 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
    - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Anne Abbott, Winnie Burnett, Charles E. Abbott, Mrs. David Nelson re Jesse Stuart, Martha Anderson Wakefield, John B. Ritch, D.J. O'Malley, Charles Stuart, Hannah Armington, Norma Stuart Porter), 1888-1951, undated (Box-folder 4 / 8)
  - Financial Records
    - Tax statements, 1899-1938 (Box-folder 4 / 9)
    - Miscellaneous (includes bank statements, Land Office receipts, promissory notes, royalty statement), 1907-1948 (Box-folder 4 / 10)
  - Legal Documents
    - Miscellaneous (includes seed lien, crop mortgage, land patents), 1909-1911, 1938 (Box-folder 4 / 11)
  - Miscellany
    - Autograph book, invitations, 1885, 1918-1934 (Box-folder 4 / 12)
- Mary Inez Abbott Swanson Matejcek
  - General Correspondence
    - Helena Huntington Smith [Mrs. H.F. Pringle], 1939 (Box-folder 4 / 13)
    - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Jack Abbott, J.B. Aubuchon, Howard Conwell Jr., Grace Harris, Ralph D. Hartman, Lucille Kennedy, Charles J. Shields, Inez Schofield, Mrs. Tom Shaw, John L. Temple, Johnnie Young), 1931-1953 (Box-folder 4 / 14)
  - Court Papers
    - Subpoena, 1949 (Box-folder 4 / 15)
  - Financial Records
    - Tax assessment list, 1952 (Box-folder 4 / 16)
  - Miscellany
    - "My Ladye's 'At Home' Book," "The Voice of the Grass," an annotated dictionary, undated (Box-folder 4 / 17)
    - Sketchbook (also used by James and Granville Stuart), undated (Box-folder 4 / 18)
    - Sketching instruction book, 1857 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
- Robert And Granville Abbott
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - To Granville Abbott (postcard from friend), undated (Box-folder 5 / 2)
  - Miscellany
    - Robert and Granville Abbott notebooks, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 5 / 3)
- Katie Stuart
  - Miscellany
    - Katie Stuart autograph book, 1881-1887 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
- Transfers To Other Programs
  - Transfers
    - List of printed material transferred to the Library, undated (Box-folder 5 / 5)
    - List of photographs transferred to the Photograph Archives, undated (Box-folder 5 / 6)